RITIK KUMAR

Bhilai, Chhattisgarh, India

J +919334623398
ritik9802official@gmail.com thttps://www.linkedin.com/in/ritik-kumar-886a1422b the first three three transfer of the first three transfer of the first three transfer of thr

https://github.com/ritik-912 https://www.youtube.com/@ritik22912

SUMMARY

Data Scientist with over 1 year of experience in AI and data analysis, specializing in machine learning and natural language processing. Notable projects include an AI-based legal document assistant and a research internship on complex networks. Demonstrated leadership as Vice President of a Literature Club and Editor of a university newsletter. Eager to apply skills in data visualization and analysis to drive innovative solutions.

EDUCATION

University Teacing Department, Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University

Dec 2021 - Present

B. Tech. CSE(HONS.) Data Science 6th Semester

Chhattisgarh, India

5th semester 69.2%

Loyola High School Jun 2018 - Apr 2020

Higher Secondary: Kurj, Patna, Bihar, India

Gyanodaya Gurukul, West Bailey Road

Apr 2016 - Apr 2018

Secondary: 84%

Dinapore, India

CERTIFICATIONS

- AI for INDIA 2.0: GUVI Geek Networks, IITM Research Park | August 2023
- Data Analysis with Python: freecodecamp.org | August 2023
- Full Stack Web Development with ReactJS, Angular and NodeJS: Udemy | August 2023
- Android Development: Centre for Skill Development and Informal Education, Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand technical University, Bhilai C.G. | September 2022

PROJECTS

Financial Relevant Fact Extraction

Apr 2024 - May 2024

Mar 2024 - Apr 2024

Olmo-7B and llama3-8b-Instruct FineTuned on FinQA dataset for Relevant Facts Extraction

Financial Sentiment Analysis

Omo-7B and llama3 finetuned on "Trillion Dollar Words: A New Financial Dataset"

Text2Speech Model based on sentiment of text

Feb 2024 - Mar 2024

- Task Assigned by Supervisor under ongoing Internship
- Collected audio dataset with emotions
- Preprocessed Sentiment analysis of text using OpenAI API
- · Given Reference audio based on classified sentiment
- Two models implemented: WHisperSpeech by openai and TTS by coqui-ai

Financial Fraud Detection notebook

Jan 2024 - Jan 2024

- Task Assignment of Internship Application by Insaid Company
- The dataset of transaction provided by Insaid used to train Random Forest and Desicion Tree Classifier

AI Based Legal Word Document Assistant

Oct 2023 - Jan 2024

- Minor Project 5th Semester
- · Answers Legal queries
- Works on embedding query search model
- Answered legal queries using an AI-based model, improving response accuracy and efficiency
- Answered legal queries using an AI-based model, improving response accuracy and efficiency

Online React Based Code Editor

Aug 2023 - Sep 2023

• Vocational Training Project 4th Semester

• Compile simple codes of programming languages

Feb 2023 - Mar 2023 **Timetable Generator**

- Independent Project 3rd Semester
- Pyhton GUI for generating timetables for educational institutions

SKILLS

- languages: hindi, english
- programming languages: c, c++, python, r
- tools: git
- Others: technical support, volunteering, editor, designer, data science, machine learning, natural language processing, data visualization, data analysis

WORK EXPERIENCE

Complex Networks Research Group Laboratory, Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur	Feb 2024 - Jun 2024
Research Intern	West Bengal, India
Training and Placement Cell, UTD, Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai	Nov 2023 - Present
Vice President	Chhattisgarh, India
University Teaching Department, Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai	Oct 2023 - Jan 2024
AI Based Legal Word Document Assistant Project Member	Chhattisgarh, India
University Teaching Department, Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai	Jul 2022 - Mar 2024
Newsletter Editor and Designer	Chhattisgarh, India

Literature Club, University Teaching Department, Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, BhilaiMar 2022 - Dec 2022 Vice President

Chhattisgarh, India